<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Annie Vella</title>
    <link>http://annievella.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Annie Vella</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright 2023 Annie Vella</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 13:00:00 +1200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://annievella.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2023 In Review: A Year of Rediscovery and Growth</title>
      <link>http://annievella.com/posts/2023-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 13:00:00 +1200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://annievella.com/posts/2023-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Returning to work after the holiday season, I find myself reflecting on a rather remarkable 2023. It was a year where innovative technologies like generative AI and advancements in quantum computing moved beyond mere buzzwords, inspiring me to delve deeper into my curiosity and passions. This reawakening not only captured my attention but also reinforced my belief in the transformative power of technology. Discovering Deming and his philosophy was a turning point for me, providing clarity and reinforcing my principles in quality, continuous improvement and leadership.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking a Swing on the Engineer/Manager Pendulum</title>
      <link>http://annievella.com/posts/taking-a-swing-on-the-engineer-manager-pendulum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 08:30:00 +1200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://annievella.com/posts/taking-a-swing-on-the-engineer-manager-pendulum/</guid>
      <description>I felt that my first proper blog post after a 10+ year blogging hiatus should be one about something that I’m really passionate about and close to my heart, so let’s dive into a topic that’s been on my mind for years.
Many of us who embark upon a career in tech do so because we love working with computers. We become engineers because we’re curious beings, who thrive on the challenge of solving tricky problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to blogging</title>
      <link>http://annievella.com/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 22:00:00 +1200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://annievella.com/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>After a long break from blogging, I&amp;rsquo;m back. Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling the urge to write down my thoughts, and I figured I may as well publish them in a way that maybe, just maybe, someone else might get something out of my musings as well.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
